Alex Pliutau

email <u>a.pliutau@gmail.com</u>

Blogs <u>pliutau.com</u>, <u>packagemain Youtube channel</u>

Stackoverflow <u>plutov</u>
Github <u>plutov</u>
LinkedIn <u>pltvs</u>

Phone +4915901497397 Location Berlin, Germany.

Objective

Professional software development with 10 years of experience bringing products from concept to release in a variety of environments and companies.

Organizational and leadership skills garnered from multiple supervisory positions, including but not limited to: mentoring, appropriate delegation, flat organizational communication, task assignment & assistance.

Love challenges, clean code, concise documentation, clear communication and constructive feedback.

My biggest strengths are APIs, Containers, Cloud, Web, Microservices. Currently I like to use Go to build scalable and fault tolerant backend systems.

Education

2007 - 2012 Belarusian State University of Informatics and Radioelectronics (Computer Science Bachelor's degree).

Experience

Solsten / Engineering Lead

Berlin, Germany January 2019 - Now

• Architecting and developing a Cloud-native backend for a company product from scratch using Microservices, Go, Kubernetes.

- Partner with other departments such as UX, Data, R&D to ensure the success of the company's products.
- Manage, coach, and lead a team of 10+ engineers, including reviewing their performance and goals and providing ongoing professional development.
- Contributing to interviewing, hiring, and training new engineers.

Wizeline / Engineering Manager

Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam May 2018 - September 2018

- Coordinate and direct projects, making detailed plans to accomplish goals and directing the integration of technical activities.
- Led > 100 technical interviews.
- Improving the interview process, by preparing new on-site challenges.
- Running internal training programs.
- Projects bootstrapping.

Wizeline / Senior Software Engineer

Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam March 2017 - May 2018

- Leading a team of engineers to build Facebook Messenger Bot, using Node.js for API, Wit.ai for NLU.
- Working with the DevOps team to build the most suitable testing / production environment using Docker, Kubernetes and AWS ECS.
- Same backend platform was used later for Google Home Voice Bot.
- Building Google Home Voice Bot with AWS Lambda and Serverless.
- Building Air Quality Google Action with Go, GCP and Dialogflow.
- Building a facial recognition office assistant using Go, Tensorflow. This project won a local hackathon in 2018.
- Held few internal and public tech talks: Microservices with Go, The Art of Git.

Lazada / Senior Software Engineer

Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam October 2014 - March 2017

- Leading development subteam in DevOps team. Lazada has a huge Microservices-based architecture (>100 services) and it requires tools and processes to manage it, DevOps team is a very important team there, responsible for downtime-less deployments, testing environments on Kubernetes, CI / CD on jenkins.
- Microservice Kit. Web and CLI project to create a new microservice based on a standard template, creates CI / CD jobs, assigns ports, adds middlewares, configures deployment. Golang, Docker, Kubernetes, Beanstalkd, Jenkins.
- Developed a tool for Data Migrations. Web tool to run data migrations / fixtures for deployments. Golang, MySQL.

Tuffle / Senior Fullstack Engineer

Minsk, Belarus November 2012 - September 2014

Managing a team of 6 engineers to build a social network platform. I was responsible for the whole application lifecycle: APIs, Testing, Infrastructure. Technologies we used: PHP, MySQL, MongoDB, Memcached, Nginx.

iTechArt / Software Engineer

Minsk, Belarus August 2010 - October 2012

I was working in the Backend team providing services for clients. At that time I mostly used PHP and it's frameworks such as Zend Framework. Was working on security optimizations for web projects, protecting the system from SQL injections, CSRF, XSS.

Languages

Belarusian Fluent

English Upper intermediate